Preliminary Guide to the William Huse Dunham, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Huse Dunham, Jr. papers
1952-1973
MS 856
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
The papers consist of correspondence relating to Dunham's research and writing as a professor of history and chairman of the department at Yale University and his political activity as a consultant to the Central Intelligence Agency. Correspondents include Joseph T. Curtis, Lewis Perry Curtis, K. Harvard Drake, Wallace Notestein, George Wilson Pierson, Frederick Bernays Weiner, and Louis Booker Wright.
Dunham, William Huse, 1901-1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William H. Dunham, Jr., 1974.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These papers consist of portions of personal and professional correspondence selected by William H. Dunham, Jr., and given to Yale University in 1974. Included are letters exchanged with American and European scholars, Yale faculty and administrators (especially those connected with the History Department), professional societies, publishers and editors of Dunham's writings, federal and state political figures, the C.I.A. (for which Dunham worked as a consultant in the 1950s), and friends and acquaintances. Among the papers are also newspaper clippings, printed matter, photographs, and financial papers. Subjects of discussion include Dunham's research and writing, other professional activities, particularly in connection with his position as professor and department chairman at Yale, and his political and social activities. Correspondents with whom there is a substantial amount of correspondence include Joseph T. Curtis, Lewis P. Curtis, K. Howard Drake, Wallace Notestein, George Pierson, Frederick Bernays Wiener, and Louis Booker Wright. There is also a file of letters of recommendation written for students and faculty members between 1956 and 1961.
The correspondence has been roughly sorted alphabetically by author, but is otherwise completely unprocessed.
Biographical / Historical
William Huse Dunham received his B.A. from Yale in 1923, and his Ph.D. in 1929. He was an instructor in history at Yale from 1925-1930, an assistant professor from 1930-1940, an associate professor from 1940-1946, a professor from 1946-1948, the George Burton Adams Professor of History from 1948-1970, and the George Burton Adams Professor of History Emeritusfrom 1970 onward.
United States -- Politics and government; Educators; Historians; Curtiss, Joseph T., 1901-1992; Curtis, Lewis Perry, 1900-1976; Drake, K. Harvard; Dunham, William Huse, 1901-1982; Notestein, Wallace, 1878-1969; Pierson, George Wilson, 1904-1993; Weiner, Frederick Bernays; Wright, Louis B. (Louis Booker), 1899-1984; United States. Central Intelligence Agency; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Department of History
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1952-1973
    - A-H (Box 1, Folder 1 - 8)
    - H (cont.)-R (Box 2, Folder 9 - 18)
    - S-Z (Box 3, Folder 19 - 26)
  - Letters of Recommendation
    - Undergraduates, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Graduate students, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Faculty, 1958-1961 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Acknowledgments of letters of recommendation, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 31)